Belkhouja, Taha

School of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Washington State University Pullman, WA

♀ tahabelkhouja.github.io **►** taha.belkhouja@gmail.com

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My general research interests are in are of robust and trustworthy machine learning. My current research focuses on developing efficient algorithms and theory to improve reliability and safety of deep learning algorithms for diverse problem settings and data domains. My current work includes:

- Robust deep learning for the time-series domain with diverse applications including mobile health, smart grid, and human activity monitoring.
- Trustworthy machine learning for sequential data with a focus on out-of-distribution detection.
- Uncertainty quantification for reliable machine-learning using conformal prediction.

EDUCATION

Washington State University, Pullman, WA

2019 – Current

Doctor of Philosophy in Computer Science - GPA 3.96

Advisor: Prof. Jana Doppa

• Thesis: Novel Directions for Reliable and Safe Machine Learning: Algorithms and Theory

University of Idaho, Moscow, ID

Master of Science in Electrical Engineering - GPA: 4.0

2017 - 2019

Advisor: Prof. Sameh Sorour

• Thesis Title: Efficient Security Schemes for Wireless Implantable Medical Devices

University of Padova, Padova, Italy

Exchange Program in Information Technology Engineering Program

2015 - 2016

• Focus Area: Optical Communication.

Higher School of Communications of Tunis (SUPCOM), Ariana, Tunisia

Engineering degree in Telecommunication - Graduated with Excellence

2013 - 2016

• Thesis Title: Experimental Characterization of Distributed Fiber Optic Pressure Sensors

Preparatory School For Engineering Studies of Tunis (IPEIT), Tunis, Tunisia

University first cycle studies

2011 - 2013

• Major: Mathematics-Physics

Professional Appointments

Research Intern

June 2022 – Aug 2022

Computer Science Lab - SRI International, USA

• Trustworthy machine learning with a focus on sequential data: Out-of-distribution detection for sequential traffic data with multiple driving agents using deep learning and neuro-symbolic regularization.

Research Assistant

May 2021 - Current

EECS Department - Washington State University, USA,

• Novel Directions for Reliable and Safe Machine Learning: Algorithms and Theory.

Belkhouja, Taha

Teaching Assistant

Aug 2019 - current

EECS Department - Washington State University, USA

- CptS 315 Introduction to Data Mining (Spring-2020, Spring-2021)
- CptS 570 Machine Learning (Fall-2020)
- CptS 223 Advanced Data Structures in C++ (Fall-2020)
- CptS 451 Introduction to Database Systems (Spring-2020)
- CptS 440/540 Artificial Intelligence (Fall-2019)

Summer Research Appointment

May 2019 - Aug 2019

EECS Department - Washington State University, USA

• Investigation of security vulnerabilities in machine learning algorithms

Teaching Assistant

Jan 2017 - May 2019

ECE Department - University of Idaho, USA

- ECE 241 Digital Logic Circuit Lab
 - ECE 311 Microelectronics I Lab

Research Assistant

Jan 2017 - May 2019

ECE Department - University of Idaho, USA

• Light-weight security schemes for wireless Implantable Medical Devices

Graduation Project Internship

Mar 2016 – Aug 2016

University of Padova, Padova, Italy

ullet Design and experimental characterization of distributed fiber optic pressure sensors based on a novel structure

Research Intern Jun 2015 – Aug 2015

GresCom Research Lab, Tunis, Tunisia

• Study and analysis of end-to-end performances of Free Space Optical transmission systems

Software Engineering Intern

Oct 2014 – Apr 2015

DisruptCK, Tunisia

• Design and implementation of a desktop application for detecting, identifying and recognition of humans in video streams

Awards and Honors

• Voiland College of Engineering, Outstanding Teaching Assistant from the School of EECS	2021
• Best Graduate Student Teaching Assistant in Computer Science	2021
Mahmoud M. Dillsi Family Graduate Fellowship	2020
• Alfred Suksdorf Fellowship	2019
• Third Prize in UIdaho 3-Minute Thesis Competition	2019
• Best Graduate Research Presentation Award, ECE Spring Colloquium	2018
• Distinctive Entrepreneurial Project Prize for Sustainable Development	2014
• Top 5% in the National Qualification Exam for Engineering Schools Entrance	2013

PUBLICATIONS

Papers Under Review

- 1. S. Ghosh, Y. Shi, T. Belkhouja, Y. Yan, J. Doppa, and B. Jones **Probabilistically Robust Conformal Prediction**. 26th International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS), 2023.
- 2. S. Ghosh, T. Belkhouja, Y. Yan, and J. Doppa. Improving Uncertainty Quantification of Deep Classifiers via Neighborhood Conformal Prediction: Novel Algorithm and Theoretical Analysis. 37th AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), 2023.
- 3. T. Belkhouja, Y. Yan, and J. Doppa. **Detecting Out-of-Distribution Time-Seires data using Deep Generative Models**. ACM Transactions on Intelligent Systems and Technology (TIST), 2022.

Belkhouja, Taha 2 of 4

4. T. Belkhouja, Y. Yan, and J. Doppa. **Dynamic Time Warping based Adversarial Framework for Time-Series Data**. IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (TPAMI), 2022. Revision submitted.

Journal Papers

- 1. T. Belkhouja and J. Doppa. Adversarial Framework with Certified Robustness for Time-Series Data via Statistical Features. Journal of Artificial Intelligence Research (JAIR), 2022.
- 2. T. Belkhouja, J. Doppa. Analyzing Deep Learning for Time-Series Data through Adversarial Lens in Mobile and IoT Applications. IEEE Transactions on Computer-Aided Design of Integrated Circuits and Systems (TCAD), 2020.
- 3. T. Belkhouja, X. Du, A. Mohamed, A.K. Al-Ali, M. Guizani. **Biometric-based Authentication Scheme for Implantable Medical Devices during Emergency Situations**. Future Generation Computer Systems Elsevier, 2019.
- 4. T. Belkhouja, X. Du, A. Mohamed, A.K. Al-Ali, M. Guizani. Symmetric Encryption Relying on Chaotic Henon System for Secure Hardware-Friendly Wireless Communication of Implantable Medical Systems. Journal of Sensor and Actuator Networks, 2018.

Conference Papers

- 1. T. Belkhouja, Y. Yan, and J. Doppa. **Training Robust Deep Models for Time-Series Domain:** Novel Algorithms and Theoretical Analysis. 36th AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence, 2022.
- 2. D. Hussein*, T. Belkhouja*, G. Bhat, and J. Doppa. Reliable Machine Learning for Wearable Activity Monitoring: Novel Algorithms and Theoretical Guarantees. International Conference on Computer-Aided Design (ICCAD), 2022. (* denotes equal contribution)
- 3. T. Belkhouja, S. Sorour, M. Hefeida. Role-based Hierarchical Medical Data Encryption for Implantable Medical Devices. IEEE Global Communications Conference (GlobeCom), 2019.
- 4. T. Belkhouja, X. Du, A. Mohamed, A.K. Al-Ali, M. Guizani. Light-Weight Solution to Defend Implantable Medical Devices Against Man-In-The-Middle Attack. IEEE Global Communications Conference (GlobeCom), 2018.
- 5. T. Belkhouja, X. Du, A. Mohamed, A.K. Al-Ali, M. Guizani. Salt Generation for Hashing Schemes based on ECG readings for Emergency Access to Implantable Medical Devices. International Symposium on Networks, Computers and Communications (ISNCC), 2018.
- 6. T. Belkhouja, X. Du, A. Mohamed, A.K. Al-Ali, M. Guizani. Light-weight encryption of wireless communication for implantable medical devices using henon chaotic system. Wireless Networks and Mobile Communications International Conference (WINCOM), 2017.
- 7. T. Belkhouja, X. Du, A. Mohamed, A.K. Al-Ali, M. Guizani. New Plain-Text Authentication Secure Scheme for Implantable Medical Devices with Remote Control. IEEE Global Communications Conference (GlobeCom), 2017.

Professional and Outreach Activities

PROGRAM COMMITTEE

- International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS), 2023
- AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence Safe and Robust AI Track, 2023

Belkhouja, Taha 3 of 4

MENTORSHIP

- Have mentored Tyler Cleveland, an undergraduate student pursuing a Computer Science degree at WSU during Summer and Fall 2020. Tyler aims to pursue graduate school in the field of Machine Learning in the future (currently working at Microsoft).
 - Mentoring two junior PhD students Chibuike Ugwu and Azza Fadhel (Fall 2022 to present).

ORGANIZATIONS

• TEDxUIdaho: Team member, Volunteer coordinator and Speaker curator, Moscow, ID.	2019
• TEDxSupCom: Team leader, Webmaster and Community builder, Tunisia.	2014
• IT Innovation organization (NetLinks): Technical manager, Tunisia.	2015-2016

TECHNICAL/PROFESSIONAL EVENTS

• Volunteer for AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence	2020
• Volunteer for Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)	2019
• TEDxSupCom second edition	2015
• IONS Tunisia: First North African International OSA (The Optical Society) Network	
of Students conference	2015
• OpenUp: Cultural event supporting diversity and underrepresented students minorities	2015
• LUPA: Lighting Up Africa Tunisia, Optics and Photonics conference	2015
• National Engineering School Forum: Higher School of Communications of Tunis representative	2014
• ACM ICPC: Tunisian Collegiate Programming Contest	2013

LANGUAGES

Arabic: NativeFrench: BilingualEnglish: ProfessionalGerman: Basic

Belkhouja, Taha 4 of 4